[Music]
[Applause]
now
[Music]
Krishna
Krishna Krishna kishna
[Music]
Harish kishish
[Applause]
[Music]
Krishna
Krishna Krishna Krishna
[Music]
[Applause]
kishish
[Music]
[Applause]
Krishna
Krishna Krishna Krishna
[Music]
[Applause]
halish kishish
[Music]
[Applause]
kishish kishna
[Music]
[Applause]
kishish
[Music]
kishna
kishna kishna kishna
[Applause]
[Music]
kishish kishish
[Applause]
[Music]
kishna
kishna kishna kishna
[Applause]
[Music]
kishish kishna
[Applause]
[Music]
Krishna
kishna kishna kishna
[Applause]
[Music]
chish
[Applause]
[Music]
har
Krishna
Krishna Krishna Krishna
[Music]
can like to start with some
[Applause]
meditation make your face soft
breathe
deeply be very very quiet don't
[Applause]
move relax your mouth relax your lips
very quiet don't
move relax your eyelids very soft
eyelids the creases in your eyelids are
so
your tummy is pulled in a little bit to
this in your
back then slowly start to come to your
breath watch your breath
let the Mind rub up against the breath
keep the mind
in contact with the breath breath will
move the Mind stays
still for
come to watch your thoughts take a piece
of your mind take a small piece of your
mind let it separate from the main
mind let it come
back away from the
mind I like to imagine it's coming out
of the back of my
head small piece of my
mind and now it's going to watch my main
mind think its thoughts so
it's like watching a
conversation I'm watching my mind as it
listens to the thoughts which rise don't
try to control the
thoughts just watch the mind listening
to the thoughts that come up because of
karma for
now please see how many of the thoughts
are about the
future how many thoughts are about
tonight or tomorrow or next
week don't try to change them just watch
how many thoughts are about the
past what happened last week last month
last
year don't try to change them just
thisen what
thoughts about the noise outside are
future thoughts your mind is planning to
go there
listen bring it back
now stop the future thoughts stop the
past
thoughts if you have a thought about the
past if you haven't thought about the
future stop it bring the mind to the to
this
place these
people no thoughts about the
future no thoughts about the
past all thoughts here in this room
slowly come back to your breath
when you're ready you can open your
eyes you can stretch your arms
you watch your neighbor
so like uh I don't know 15 years ago I
got a phone call I was living in New
York and
um this guy said hi I'm Swami
s you know and just to hear the word
Swami I was kind of like uhoh you know
some Swami
going and uh he said I I live in the
shivananda center in uh the Bahamas so I
didn't know where the Bahamas was I knew
it was some Island okay and then he said
uh we're having an Interfaith program
and it was basically our token Buddhist
cancelled on us and you got your name do
you want to be the toen bu you know and
I was like
No and then uh we were working really
hard on atip release a release of
ancient books on CD and uh we were
really really busy there was a team of
five people with me on it uh on six
street so we were like working night and
day you know then he called me again you
know oh please come you know I said I
can't I got to fin I got a dead line we
have to finish this DVD it has a
thousand ancient books on it so it was a
lot of work and
and you know I said we don't we just
don't have time we we got to finish this
he said okay look how many people in
your office I said five you know he said
we'll fly you all
down uh you stay in the my house boat he
has a house boat on the
bay and uh all five of you can stay on
the house boat I'll move
out and uh you can keep working on the
CD while you're in the house Boo and
then you just have to come out for an
hour and talk a couple times you know
then I'm like okay
and uh so we went it was really funny
Robert Shelton I think punok was there I
think l or was there it was cute and we
finished the CD on the house for and you
know we went
swimming but then I got to know them and
and so I've been going every year right
except for the threee retreat I think
I've gone every year to talk there and
it's been very nice uh we we did the
yoga Sutra we team taught the yoga Sutra
and then to Pi up some of that and um it
was interesting cuz they're hardcore
at Hindu shankara system you know and
we're hardcore Buddhist to you know but
a thousand years ago we all used to be
together uh we all used to practice
together and uh then some of us went to
Tibet and then the British came to India
and uh but anyway now we started getting
back together and it's been very sweet
and and we're both really hardcore Swami
G is a great teacher and he's a very he
was trained directly by Swami Vish
Deanda who's the student of shivananda
he would he lived with him for like 30
years and I lived with my Lama for 25
years so we're hardcore and it's kind of
a sweet relationship you know and uh so
anyway he's like well what do we do next
year we finished all the sutras and
stuff and I said well I'd like to teach
Nirvana I'd like to take teach about
Nirvana so last year at this time I
taught about Nirvana you
know and then he was uh well what are we
going to do next year you know and I'm
like you know Swami G I got more demands
on my time now than I used to have you
know and I don't know if I can come down
here for 10 days or 7 days you know
could we do half the program in New
York with your Center in New York York
and then have to program in the Bahamas
so then I have only I'll make all my New
York students happy and then I only have
to come here for 3 days I was kind of
tricking him and uh he said okay and uh
so we had this idea that uh you know we
would keep going on the subject of Nana
and we would do three days in New York
hopefully Swami
sash who's a great uh teacher will be
coming tomorrow here from the center in
uh New York he runs to shiv the center
in New York these centers are old we
just went to the one in Montreal it just
had its 50th
anniversary and they've been they
cranked out 10,000 yoga teachers they
they just finished their 10,000th person
month monthlong yoga training uh and
it's a beautiful training and it's a
good good lineage very good lineage and
they're all celibate in the Bahamas and
it's kind of nice to be there and and uh
they're all very beautiful people uh
they're all EX Israeli intelligence
officers
uh most hot right uh but they're
beautiful they're kind of cool and uh
they're really intense people it's a
pleasure to be there also they have this
white beach with turquoise water it's
never
choppy you know you can see her feet and
all the fish under there and it's really
beautiful uh it was a Coconut Grove 40
years ago and some lady gave it to SW
May Bish gave on the uh the Atlanta's
Hotel chain and Club Med on one side and
George Harrison's EST State on the other
side and uh so they're like trying to
get the land away from the yogis cuz
they just have these little cottages and
huts and Tents and so there they are
next to Michael Jackson what's her name
Opa
Winfrey uh Atlant Hotel George Harrison
and then there's a no Ash there and they
tried to take the land away and uh the
government stopped it cuz the government
of the Bahamas they a lot of them come
to the yoga as a lot of them like the
the current uh prime minister was a
student there so it's cool kind of sweet
you know and they're really I love the
place it's a good place they have good
yoga programs and and they're especially
good at creating
you know like throwing up on the beach
and stuff
[Applause]
and I heard there were tourist walking
down from Atlanta's house 30 people
throwing up on the beach they like all
the foods that bring good at the
ice and
uh I you call godas I think you call it
godas it's a practice okay we're not
going to do
it so anyway they all agreed the two
swammies will teach you know we will
hear the two swamis and uh so I'll teach
down there also so the idea is tonight
Wednesday Thursday night here in New
York and then uh we go down on Friday we
fly down on Friday then I'll start
Friday night teaching and then we'll do
Friday Saturday Sunday come back Monday
morning stuff like that okay uh The
Cottages there are booked out uh I
believe there's some tents SP up uh
right Dr to sakur uh you want to raise
your hand so she's in charge of the
Bahamas segment uh you can still get
into a tent the tents are comfortable
they're nice it's on a perfect white
Beach there'll probably be a hurricane I
don't know but uh
uh it's not just our program they have a
teacher training running at the same
time two teacher two teacher trainings
running so anyway they're pretty heavy
book it's good great yoga we'll do yoga
today we we'll do yoga every day
together and uh meditation
and they do all this chanting we stole
most of our chants from them but we do
them better and then
uh uh you you like it and the idea is uh
me and Swami the two swamis we thought
we would like to work on Iana is defined
in the Tibetan tradition as
[Applause]
an means your negative emotions like
jealousy anger judging other people
addictions these are called malupa means
all of them uh banga means to get rid of
them okay so Tango means
uh you are able to get rid of them
because you saw the true nature of
reality okay according to the Buddhist
idea you can't get rid of a negative
emotion without seeing Ultimate Reality
directive it's not possible you can
suppress
you can suppress your anger you can
suppress your jealousy you can manage
your addictions but you can't get rid of
them permanently unless you understand
reality okay and I think the yoga would
say the same thing you know
Yoga Yoga means stopping your
misunderstanding of reality and then the
yoga Sutra also gives the the big cles
in their
tradition like
uh you
can so in both traditions we believe
that there are negative emotions those
are called CLA in Sanskrit okay they're
called CLA CLA has a the word klish is
the root and it has a cogn name in
English which is
Holly which means uh
prickly and CLA means uh an emotion
which bothers you
[Music]
[Applause]
the definition of eaia in in Buddhist
tradition is any thought which upsets
the Peace of Mind of the person who has
it okay so Nirvana is to stop those
thought forever okay you it would your
husband would be incapable of upsetting
him okay if you reach
nirvana uh your husband would not be
capable of upsetting you no matter how
hard he tried uh he couldn't get you
upset all right that's Nirvana okay uh
it's not the same as Enlightenment okay
Nirvana happens long before
Enlightenment Nirvana is when you can
shut down your negative emotions forever
because you understand
reality and then buddhahood comes much
later Enlightenment comes much later
Enlightenment includes the capacity to
see all things in the universe in all
times and Nana happens a lot longer
before that we're just shooting from for
Nirvana this week we'll get to
Enlightenment at some later time okay uh
so the way of this this thing about
dealing with your negativities your the
emotions that bother you are uh claa
right
bother uh there's a trick to it okay
this week uh you will learn uh and I'm
assuming some people won't get down the
Bahamas so I'll I'll give you a nice
package in the three days so don't
stress okay uh
we'll cover this stuff in the first 3
days and then we'll just keep going in
we'll go deeper in the Bahamas but
especially
offshore but
uh but uh it'll be enough if you do the
first three days and it'll be okay we're
going to present a method of dealing
with your own worst negative emotion
okay it's a new idea of how to deal with
our own worst negative emotion okay how
to turn it
around and they make us unhappy okay
that's the point that's why I came back
to New York so soon okay normally R
right six months or something every a
year but I
uh it's a beautiful subject because the
point is by the end of this week can we
be happier you see because those cles
those negative emotions they ruin your
happiness
Masa means Asanti Asanti destroys your
peace of mind okay uh it makes you
unhappy it makes you stressed it gives
you
anxiety uh it ruins your happiness okay
and you know life goes on life is moving
on uh we're all uh going through our
lives and it's sad to be unhappy if we
could be happy right uh so I my goal and
this course I could drown you with
scriptural knowledge about
Nirvana okay but I just want to make you
happier by the end of the week okay so
I'll take the the cream of the what do
you call CL the CL the cream of the
cream uh from the teachings of Nirvana
which are extensive I mean we could do
it for a year or two uh but I'll take
the cream and the cream the purpose of
the cream
is to give you a a method for managing
your Your Own Worst emotions okay
so I was talking today at the Tre Jews
and I said uh you know I wasn't a big
gang fighter when I was a kid but I got
in a few and uh there was a thing in a
gang fight uh you go after the leader of
the other gang you know basically just
run up to him and punch him in the head
and uh
and then he falls down and they all fall
apart the whole the whole resistance
falls apart and then you can just walk
home and it's all over actually it got
done to us more than we did to others uh
but somebody come up and punch my older
brother and Our Gang would fall cold so
anyway
uh if you can deal with
your your most common
negativity then the rest will crumble
okay if you have a new uh approach
to dealing with your most serious
negativity then uh the rest will crumble
but you just got to get to the worst one
first okay you you hit the first one you
hit the you hit the meanest one first
and then the rest don't if the if it's a
new system okay they can't stand
up so that means we have to
identify your wor clure okay
there are
84,000 uh
cles then there's a teaching on you know
narrows it down to 20 something okay uh
then Lama Kimberly and I worked on it we
figured 84,000 was a little much in know
three
days uh so we we worked out what we felt
we voted for
you uh the six
biggest uh negative emotions of modern
times okay it's a little different from
the San group the six classical ones in
scripture I we we talked for a long time
we've both Ted for a long time I saw her
on
Saturday and uh we've been working for a
few months actually starting in August
uh on this program and
um so we're going to tonight we'll we'll
do six uh short uh sessions in between
the blah blah by GUI Michel we'll do six
short sessions of
meditation and it's sort of an
introspection so I'll propose a
candidate for your worst uh negativity
and then you're going to examine your
heart and see when was the last time you
had it and uh we'll go through six that
we have
chosen uh and then I'd Like You by the
end of the night we'll try to have you
choose one that You' one of the six that
you'd like to work on for this week okay
so I could you know we could sit I could
read you scriptures about uh Nirvana
they are interesting they're very very
beautiful they're like going to the
what's the big museum of modern not
the the it's like going to the Met if if
you get good at
scripture uh and we have a I have a 8
million p pages in my
laptop right this is the 25th year that
we are typing uh scripture in in the
refugee camps and uh I could walk you
through those places and and you would
love it you know it's like a I don't
know they're like classic pieces of art
they are beautiful to just like got go
like going to the lou or something and
you can just stand in one room and see
Ron the whole day
and and not go to another room you can
go back for many days right we can do
that but it won't help your I'm afraid
it won't be applied to to ourselves you
know so I'm going to
stop uh I'll give you the cream of I'll
give you the best paintings there are
about Nirvana maybe we have to do more
okay someday there's more there's like
hundreds and hundreds of beautiful pages
about
n but then I think we should pause try
to look inside and see which clure is
making you unhappy right now in your
life okay if you could remove the gang
leader claa in your heart you'd be twice
as happy tomorrow okay and and isn't
that why we're here right that's the
whole point of being here so I'm trying
to we tried we worked really hard with
both the swamy G and Lama Kimberly
Nicole and everybody we
what we want is that by the end of the
week you've made some progress and I've
made some progress on our worst claer
our worst
negativity and and maybe turned it
around you see each negativity has a
corresponding positive thing right it's
interesting that uh whatever negativity
you have if you if you can work on it it
will become a strength your weakness
your worst weakness will become your
greatest strength that's the nature of
of claas is the is this
going it's set I'm really sorry about
the heat uh hang in there I guess it
kicks in around
10 uh I don't like it I like to freeze
the audience because they pay
attention um but
anyway your biggest weakness can become
your greatest strength for
example uh
he Hector introduced me uh last time I
was here last year at the school he said
the first Western
G I wasn't the first Western G there was
another
one his name is George draus he's from
Switzerland okay so people always
introduce me as the first American G but
I'm not the first Western GUI there was
another one before me
and uh this and he was he stayed a lot
in my monast Sarah he stayed in the
wrong part of Sarah s j but it's okay
and um then uh you know I would go out
and and you know Roar in the debates and
then i' I'd be S come home and sit and
drink tea with my teachers and they'd
say you're amazing you're almost as good
as
[Music]
George who is this George
is this George guy you know and then
they'd say oh he's you can't touch him
man you just got to hope you never get
into a debate with him you know and and
you know I was like I saw I hated
him long distance I I never went to his
it takes like 20 minutes to walk across
our Monastery and I never went to his
part you know and then uh I don't know
we were having a class one day and they
were talking about jealousy you know and
uh then you have this light come on in
your head hopefully you'll have a light
come on in your head this week you know
then I'm like Bing you know I'm
jealous like it's a big uh Revelation
right people if you ask a person their
worst emotion they will admit their
second
worst and they're blind to the worst
it's very interesting okay like then one
day I don't know what happened probably
somebody hit me on the head with a cupsi
but uh I I was like dang I'm jealous you
know I don't like him and there's no
reason I never met him you know so I
said I'm going to go meet George you
know and I got together some Tibetan
sweets and you know some scarves you're
supposed to take a scarf and you know I
went and knocked on his door you know
and he's like oh you're Michael you know
and I'm like yes and he said I heard
about you you know come in and then you
know I sat down and there's this tense 3
minutes when I'm like checking him WR
and uh he seems pretty nice guy actually
you know and the the upshot is that we
became very good friends you know so uh
you your greatest weakness can become
your greatest strength and we supported
each other and we helped each other and
We snuck secret t next to each other and
and you know we became like really tight
and uh if you can take your worst claa
and work on it it can become a great
strength so we became like brothers and
we became very supportive with each
other and we we we both Rose through the
ranks because we had each other to help
each other and uh so it's like that your
greatest weakness can become your
greatest strength now I'm happy when I
hear is doing well right so hopefully by
the end of the
week we can stop working on the
negativity and start developing the
opposite you see the opposite of
jealousy is is to take pleasure in the
achievements of others right and that's
a lot more fun so I don't want to spend
a whole week beating yourself up about
your jealousy uh about halfway through
this stream you know we will hopefully
change it to the
opposite and by the end of the week I
don't just want you to be a jealousy
controller I want you to be a a
celebration like I want you to go to The
Other Extreme and become someone who
really appreciates other people's
achievements and and is happy when you
hear that someone is doing well okay
so uh we have to examine our our hearts
so tonight I I'll keep stopping
and and I'll propose a candidate for
your wor place by the end of the night
I'd like you to you know see which one
clicks in
you and uh and we'll work on that okay I
could be we could be doing 12 other ones
the possibilities are endless but we s
we sort of tailored the program to six
candidates uh one of which you probably
have even if it's not your
favorite uh okay
all right and I want you
to
uh take these teachings and apply them
to yourselves each of us it's very
common to apply them to the person you
don't like next to you you know like you
hear a talk on jealousy and you're like
she could use a talk on
je like you know you want to you like
want to take him out of dinner and say I
heard some
good methods today on for work on your
jealousy so be be aware of these mental
tricks your mind will play tricks on you
okay first of all it will not admit the
the one that you are the worst at and
secondly it will it will try to apply
these these medicines to your neighbor
and not to yourself okay so work on
beware of those two be aware of those
two things it's not in in it's not
inappropriate this week in the next few
days to approach people who know you
well okay uh your friends and say you
know I'm on this sort of self-help weak
thing and uh I was wondering if here's
the six emotions that they're talking
about which one do you think applies to
me okay like people that you trust and
people who aren't trying to hurt you uh
people that you love people that you
love enough to ask the truth from them
okay then ask them in the next few days
say here are six emotions which one do
you I'm supposed to pick one I I'm
assigned to pick one of them which one
do you think applies best to me and then
listen to them and don't be angry at
them okay don't be upset at
okay people ask me all the time gu what
might get fa and I'm like I don't
know cuz I don't want them to be I don't
want them to be mad at
me
okay someone that you uh feel that you
trust and someone that that you know
loves you enough to tell you the truth
then ask them here's six you can list
the six the six are listed here I'll
tell you the six and we're going to work
on them we'll start going through them
okay again these are just candidates
they're 8
3,994
others but uh
let's work let's see which one applies
to you okay so the the exercise begins
now you're going to hear six emotions
and try to see which one I'm not trying
to make you feel bad I'm trying to make
you happy I'm trying to get rid of the
one that's hurting you the most okay and
they do they ruin your life they make
your whole life you can spend 20 years
and they will ruin your life will make
you an unhappy person so if we could get
over them this week I'm proposing I can
give you a secret weapon a secret method
of getting rid of the one The
Chronic emotional disease that you've
had for your whole life I can help you
but we have to choose it first okay so
here we go number
one guess what my number one would be
jealousy Envy in all its glorious
forms okay just don't tell me about some
good teacher who's coming here next week
okay cuz then I have to
[Applause]
smile all right
uh I'm really
glad
uh number two anger okay
anger some people think they don't have
them at all you just didn't meet the
right
circumstances okay no they say every
human soul has all
84,000 and if you if you're not
manifesting it right now it's cuz you
don't have a partner right now or
something like that
okay it's not that you got over
it I'm not jealous of art angle cuz he
moved away
okay all right anger uh number three
addictions we put ass okay addictions to
like alcohol drugs uh food sex
talking uh
email okay compulsive behavior of some
kind you can't stop yourself from doing
it and it's not good for you that you
keep doing it emailing on the internet
over an hour and a half is not good for
almost
anybody can you stop when you won you
see or can't you can you stop eating
when you're pH or can't you you see uh
do you take a glass of wine and do you
have to have a second glass of wine the
next day and has it become a he that you
can't stop okay compulsions addiction
okay uh number four
busyness okay trying to do too many
things that seems to be a modern the
more time
saving Electronics the inent the more
busy we
get
okay right
time management problems business
nervous anxious because too many things
to do and blaming it on others right
like it's all
self-imposed right your busyness is
self-imposed you want to be busy and you
make yourself more and more busy until
you're unhappy okay uh next one judging
other people okaying my llama told me
many times that's probably my number two
the second best one I do okay and these
are you know maybe judging other people
you're not aware that you're doing it
often right but you are constantly all
the time you know constantly constantly
constantly judging other people making
assumptions about people uh based on
what someone said or what they look like
like that there is a big Mongolian guy
do you
know P this is said jimy LA's s
brother so you know he's sitting with my
he used big Mongolian guy he used to
come over to the temple in New Jersey
every night to eat Momos we had to make
extra and he would just eat them and
they take a long time to me these are
dumplings and he would just polished
them off so one time my stepmother came
to visit me and she's sitting at the
table and she's trying to make
conversation with you know and he's like
well you know what do
you you know and uh you know what do you
do for a job I work you know and then
I'm like I'm like giving her signs you
know don't even try you know he just
eats and then and then she says well I'm
going to New York tomorrow to hear the
Opera and he's like Opera you know and
she's like yeah U right he say oh you
got to see the P I was there last week
you know I I have season tickets I go
every I go three times a week you know
and U the Italian one the lead guy oh
unbeliev you got to hear this guy I'll
take you you know I know the guy and
they we're all
[Applause]
like you know and then they had this
2hour conversation about Opera and you
know French Opera and stuff and I'm like
you know you judge people right we judge
people we make up stories about people
and then we force them into that story
so I think judging other people is a
very common one uh last
one
procrastination laziness putting things
off not doing what you know you should
be doing for me it's in the form of
uh Mis prioritizing things you
know like I do have to eat dessert
sometime today but somehow it gets done
before the homework for tomorrow night
n we'll talk about that
later like Mis prioritizing things you
know which all of us do I think you know
maybe you're a person who can get things
done but you're not really attacking the
most important things first right your
practice is most important and you you
put it on I can't do yoga today because
I have to
you know call somebody or something like
that like that so these are the do we
have six okay I'm going to stop there
okay and we're going to do a short
meditation and we'll do this six times
[Applause]
tonight in a group meditation it's
crucial to be quiet okay it's crucial
not to move you cannot meditate you can
just uh you know what bring your knees
up to your chest and kind of sit like
that and and doze but don't snore okay I
mean in group meditation you can really
hurt someone else by moving so if you
can't do it for yourself do it for the
other people in the room okay tr get all
your coughing out now you can control
coughing pretty well
if you focus on the tickle when it comes
okay and then suddenly it's time to end
the meditation and you didn't cough
yet then you can come here we
[Applause]
go please come to your breath watch your
breath glue the mind to the passage of
the
breath
e and I'd like you to think of the one
person in the world that you are most
jealous of what person in your life now
can bring out feelings of jealousy in
you
identify one person don't be lazy don't
be
fuzzy choose a person if you're not a
jealous type choose the person you're
most likely to be jealous about but
please come up with one person's name
who are you most envious
of in your
pick a few
candidates but narrow it down narrow the
field down to the worst
how often are you jealous of this person
does it come once a day does it come
once a week does it come every hour do
you think of them how often do you think
of them
what is it exactly about them that
they're jealous that you're jealous
of what is it that they have
that you
are unhappy that they have
slowly come back to your
breath and you can slowly open your eyes
you can stretch your hand
when I'm in a jealous uh what do you
call
it binge when I have a jealous of binge
I don't do alcohol binges I do jealousy
binges and
uh I I spend much more time thinking
about how I wish this person didn't have
what what I don't want them to have then
I think about the things that I have
already you know like I have precious
beautiful happy things
and I I think about them less than I
think about what I don't have see what I
mean this is the disease of
jealousy all right I'm going to just
intersperse those with
uh you know Nirvana
okay
uh so we're going to go through the
classical presentation of
Nirvana and
uh and then we'll start start applying
it to to our own emotion to our own con
okay I think it's useful to look at the
word Nirvana okay I I like words and uh
I like the word Nirvana and it has three
distinct meanings three the word Nirvana
has three different
meanings and uh I thought it would I
think they tie well into our project
to remove Our Own Worst negativity okay
uh the the three ways of explaining the
word Nirvana uh themselves give us a lot
of information about how I'm going how
gei Michael is going to deal with his
jealousy okay first part okay and I'm
also following your homework I want you
to do the
homework right uh there's a it's five
easy questions it's not a big deal
[Applause]
uh why
homework uh what we're offering you in
this course is I mean first of all to
deal with your own negativities but
secondly in the monastery it's a
tradition that once you listen to a
teaching you are the holder of that
teaching I'm tricking you okay I'm
dumping it on you okay uh you're the
next lineage holder all right when I
finish this Nana thought I'm done with
it in New York then it's your problem
okay uh you have to pass it out to other
people all right that's the tradition in
the mother it's a some people don't come
to a teaching because they don't want to
be they don't want that
responsibility they're they're aware
that it's a heavy responsibility okay
this teaching on Nirvana has been passed
on for 75 Generations 2 and 1 half
thousand years
we can recite the names of each lineage
holder back to the Buddha there's a few
gaps okay around the the
600s okay I don't know exactly the guy's
name all right
but I can show you the listed names back
to the Lord Buddha okay and and they
didn't lose the the lineage now it's
your problem okay and uh it's like
passing on a recipe for a cure for AIDS
is that important okay I'm giving you
the recipe that can cure something which
is worse than AIDS okay and that's cles
right and if you mess around with the
the recipe or you don't get it straight
it's like making a good cocktail you
know I'm I don't know but I'm
sure uh there are masters of it in the
world and and it takes a certain amount
of this certain amount of this and maybe
you have to add Elder flow in the cor I
see uh try to find out um as the final
touch you know that makes it just right
and then you have to listen carefully
when they tell you the recipe you have
to follow the instructions
carefully uh Nirvana's like that okay so
I'm going to give you uh detailed
instructions on Nana and you have good
authentic reading okay
but but the homework kind of forces you
to see that you got the important points
okay there's five questions on the
homework those are the points I don't
want you to screw up okay you miss one
of those then the thing is going to
taste terrible or give somebody a
headache or something like that okay so
like you have
to at least those five points you have
to get straight and then you're okay
then you'll be a good miniature holder
and I want you to hold the lineage and I
want you to pass it on so for me you
coming here is a statement that you are
willing to take on that responsibility
it's a serious responsibility hasn't
been broken in 2 and half th000 years 25
centuries don't be the schmuck who
screws it up okay like get it right okay
agree
M okay
we were at the three jws today it's a
beautiful place to teach okay and I
encourage all of you all of you should
teach okay and it's such a nice place to
break in to teaching like you're kind of
shy and you don't really know any place
that you could teach and uh you never
taught a group of people go to the three
jewels go where's Nancy Karen is she
here she's over there can you stand up
she's the director of the stre Michael
Wick in the back
if you would like to teach talk to them
okay they have free spaces it's open
it's free they don't charge you anything
they give you a chance to teach
something they help you make the posters
they help you send out the
announcements you know we have a class
at D mountain university about how to
make a sexy poster about a talk you see
what I mean not too many words not too
few you know like that find a good image
off of Google make sure it's not
copyrighted stuff like that you know and
I encourage you to approach this rituals
okay if you're not teaching now uh think
about teaching okay it could be anything
anything you think is is useful for
people you know we have classes in
French cooking uh we have uh you know
how to not be jealous when your French
cooking and and uh now we have all kinds
of cool every time we have a program in
Phoenix we have a class on solar energy
and we have different experts come and
teach solar energy and then we have uh
the last program two weeks ago two
weekends ago we had a prison training we
had a 2hour
training uh to work in prisons and
teaching prisons and uh you know we have
a great program there so think about it
okay do come up with some cool things
that you want to share it with people
and talk to them and it's free and just
go you know you might get the 6 a.m.
slot on Wednesdays but that's okay
uh and uh I want I call it a toolkit I
want you to have a toolkit of different
cool stuff that you can teach okay and
Nirvana should be in there after this
week okay you should somebody say you
want to come to J and teach you say yeah
and and they say what are you have your
tool C say I can teach nana I did the
homeworks I listened to everything
carefully I got it straight I can teach
n okay I can teach the first three days
of it
anyway okay all right okay uh by the way
if someone goes to the bamas and comes
back and you couldn't go then obviously
you should drag them to the three Jews
and and learn the second 3 days from
somebody okay maybe we can set that up
okay CU not everybody may may be able to
go all right um so the first meaning of
nirvana uh near comes is a
prefix
uh that is uh the R Used to Be an S
before V the S changes to R so it was
n uh and it comes from an older prefix
called n it's just ni okay ni is a
prefix in Sanskrit and it has the
meaning of down or
not or away okay so the the near part in
Nirvana means uh down out
away uh and it came into English in the
word nil which means
what it's like zero or nothing or
neither you can see it in the word
neither actually the word nether like
Netherland Netherlands the lower lens it
it means lower it means out it means
away it means not okay ner the ner means
that VA and in s they don't have a real
V it's more like
a
Nana
uh there can be a short a or there can
be a long a this happens to be
a long long a okay V
and that means to blow okay long means
to blow okay so in an A and A is a
suffix in ending that means the one who
does that thing okay like a comedian
does comedy mathematician does
mathematics okay it came into English
also okay so n ner one
near means the one who blows out a fire
or a candle okay what's the
[Applause]
fire G Michael's
jealousy okay all right one of those six
is the fire and it's a real fire it
makes you unhappy it ruins your life it
makes you spend your days unhappy it
ruins your time it spoils your party
life should be like a party and and your
cles spoil it all day long you know if
you didn't have them you wouldn't miss
them they don't do anything
useful okay uh they just make your day
less joyful than it could have been and
then they do that for year after year
okay so Nana means blow out blow out
those things extinguish them and the
idea is permanently okay it's not true
that Buddhism denies permanent see okay
it's not true that everything is
impermanent uh if you can blow if you
can reach nirvana it's permanent they
never come back you can't have them
again okay there's a method which is why
we're here and by the end of uh Thursday
night you will have that method whether
you apply this to yourself is another
thing right I will give you a method by
you can blow out uh your worst
negativity forever it won't come back
okay there are ways to reduce the
negativity or to suppress it meditation
is one of them okay uh peaceful
meditations uh and a yoga a good yoga
class okay they make you feel better for
a while you know you can go into a good
yoga class I had one this afternoon
right we had a nice one at the 3 uals
and um you can go in feeling cranky or
you know upset and you sweat and you
work hard or you can do a nice long
meditation and you breathe well and and
you get calm right and that will
suppress negative emotions for a while
you know then you get in your
car move into
traffic three
really I almost Ed the bad word three
irritating people cut you off and then
suddenly the effects of the yoga are
gone or you're at work and you've got
your employees is acting up and you know
suddenly all the meditation dissolves
and you get angry okay
irritated these are temporary methods uh
I'm going to teach you an ultimate one
okay that doesn't suppress it it removes
it and it can't come back
okay and it's difficult to imagine what
you're life would be without your
claes it's difficult to imagine what
life would be if you could not get upset
or you could not get jealous or you
could not get angry or you had no
addictions at all okay it's hard to
imagine uh but I think you'll get a
taste of it by the end of this week okay
and then you get uh addicted to that
okay you get addicted to not having
addictions and it's sweet and you feel
happy and you feel lighter and suddenly
life is is is much more bright and happy
and more Sunny everything is magical and
fresh and you just feel like engaged and
happy and joyful all the time and try to
imagine what it's like not to have any
claes to blow them out okay that's the
proposal we are not treating them we are
destroying them okay in fact there's a
Tibetan word uh for a person in the rich
is our heart our heart means uh someone
who destroyed the enemy Hut means Han H
H comes from Han like Han is related to
H as in
a
h no no hurting right it came into
English as H came into English as gun
hes become G's in the word gun comes
from AR means enemy
in Sanskrit our heart means person who
destroy the enemy that's
someone yeah I trans say as full
Destroyer sometimes like enemy
Destroyer a person who has reached
nirvana is called an
Arad AR they have killed the enemy not
suppressed
it uh by a good yoga class or or a good
meditation cuz it will come back they
have destroyed it it's not they're not
capable of getting upset at work anymore
okay like that very beautiful our heart
we want to be our heart okay all right
that's the first meaning of n now I'll
give you another
one uh oh by the way the V the V part
came into English as fan or
ventilation okay or wind uh meaning to
blow okay so blow out
Nirvana there's another n meaning
there's another interpretation of
Nirvana that Lord Buddha once talked
about uh there's a beautiful Sutra
called the Sutra of the great Nirvana
somebody should translate it something I
don't think it's been translated it's
unbelievable it's psyched
deling uh it's like a Jimmy Hendrick
song or something it's really good and
really intense really beautiful and uh
in that Sut of the great Nirvana he he
gives a lot of these explanations one is
there's a another roote Sanskrit root VA
which means uh to
weave uh a web a spider web or a carpet
or an
illusion uh V to weave a lot of times
English cognates or related English
words are created by the duplication of
the room okay so for something that you
do habitually like weaving is is what do
you call repetitive so they they
duplicate the root so it becomes vaa and
and then A's become e in English so it's
weave the word weave comes from V
meaning to weave okay near weave means
to break the weaving to destroy the
weaving to destroy the illusion okay so
you can read Nirvana as uh
destroying the web which you have woven
around you
yog you can
destroy the
illusion the web of Illusion that you
have created around you
okay that's a beautiful interpretation
because it help tells you how to get to
the first meaning of
nirvana okay first meaning is blow out
your anger
forever second meaning is destroy the
illusion that's causing you to get angry
and then you will blow out you see if
you can destroy the weaving you can blow
out uh your negativity okay so let's go
to the second one I think it's
[Applause]
anger yeah ready let's meditate for just
a second
[Music]
[Applause]
do all your what do you call
it fidgeting and then when you're ready
become like a piece of concrete okay
here we
[Applause]
go please come to your breath loosen
your
face sucking your tummies lightly
straighten your
back loosen your lips loosen your
eyes and then quickly before your mind
can object come to your breath watch
your
breath for
bring to mind the person in your life
who most has the capacity to upset you
who in your
life is best at pushing your buttons who
who can make you upset
quickest again candidates will come to
me mind and pick the master of upsetting
let your mind roll over the people in
your life and select the ones who upset
you
and I'd like you to play back the video
of the most recent timely OB C
what what exactly happened where were
you what did they
do then made you
upset don't get upset again okay you're
meditating
come back to your
breath open your
eyes stretch if you want too
[Applause]
okay if you need to stand up and stretch
[Music]
your and we'll just do a few more
minutes and then we'll take a break
uh how does the weaving of an illusion
apply here and how can we unweave it n
right how can we unwe n so here the N
means un invol means leaving right F how
can what is the particular illusion
which is being woven here and how does
it help us blow out um getting upset
okay
[Applause]
I don't know in my case uh somebody was
supposed to do something and they didn't
do it okay
um so I I felt that the person had
committed to do something and then they
they let me go
[Applause]
okay then in this
system uh that perception is coming from
me right that person is coming from what
they did is coming from a SE seed in my
mind as a karmic seed exists in my mind
and as it opens I hear the words from
someone that they didn't do what they
were supposed to do okay uh and I'm not
going to go into the pen thing cuz it's
too late in the day too many people will
F me maybe tomorrow okay we can explain
kic seeds and we will okay right now
let's not go deeper into it uh there's a
seed in my mind as it opens I hear the
person say I didn't do what what you
asked me to do
[Applause]
okay it's important to understand that
no one in the world has the ability to
put a seed in my mind except me okay as
much as you may want to put a seed in
someone else's mind or as much as you
may want to blame someone else for a
seed that you have in your mind the fact
is a seed can only be put in your mind
by yourself okay H uh so I let somebody
down recently all right in the last few
weeks maybe I was supposed to get a
homework ready for a class and uh I let
them down it's a lot easier to be the
letter downer than the letter down e
right like you hardly notice it when
you're the letter
Downer okay and then uh I mean it's just
I was busy and I'm not a bad person I I
had eight readings to do on the plane
yesterday three for
Bahamas two for New York one for three
jewels uh one from
Princeton uh one from Moscow one from
zor
and one for
Hamburg okay so I was busy it's not like
I'm AER you know and uh it's okay that I
didn't get it done okay the person who
let you down thought the same
thing they were also busy and they also
had many other things to do okay and
they are coming from you they reflect
your own thinking perfectly because they
are coming from you you okay so this
person who couldn't do what you asked
them to do the person who let you down
they are coming from a seed in your mind
that you planted a week ago when you let
someone else
down okay so you can't blame this person
right they're they're not the guilty
party who's the guilty party you are all
right I'm giving you a
there's an
illusion that they are the guilty party
because there's an illusion of Free Will
in their behavior okay you think if they
had chosen differently they could have
done what you asked them to do and not
something else that they did right you
assume that you
think they could have done what I asked
them to do but they didn't they did
something else they made a decision to
do something else they could have
decided to do what I wanted them to do
right that's
false okay that's false they didn't have
a choice okay from your perception they
must do whatever seeds you have in your
mind forc them to do okay it's
interesting all right you don't have a
choice they didn't have a choice forget
the thinking that they had a choice if
you grasp that they had no choice but to
do what they did because of your own
seeds and your own past actions you
can't be
upset okay it's not possible to be upset
we are never upset at ourselves we only
get upset at other people I'm not upset
that I didn't finish the homework for
tomorrow I'm fine with
it but I get upset when somebody else
doesn't do what they promised me okay
like that right so
uh on un weeing the illusion that they
had a choice they didn't have a choice
it not it's not their fault it's your
fault okay unweave that illusion that
it's their fault it's not their fault
that's Nirvana which leads the
Nana okay it blowing
up getting upset you can't get
upset at someone else if it's your fault
right in theory the first time you hear
that should be enough in practice I
don't I can't say how long it takes cuz
I haven't seen you I've been doing it
for 30 40
years maybe you'll be a little
faster okay but that's that's the
illusion you break that illusion
n and you get to Nana and you don't get
upset anymore okay all right we're going
to take a break uh please come back
at let's say 10 right what
[Music]
time okay so it's about a 15 minute
break please come back at 10 I'll be
here if you want to talk or you have
some thing that you want to ask about if
you have any class that you are teaching
if you have any program that you are
giving all the way down to so
[Applause]
Nico okay I got you all right talk to
Nicole can you stand up okay and we're
going to put it into a free flyer for
everyone that's here okay all right have
a nice break